Lois Dodd
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Lois Dodd papers
1949-2001
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Dodd, Lois
2.0 linear feet
The papers of New York City painter, educator, gallery owner, and activist Lois Dodd date from 1949 to 2001 and measure 2.0 linear feet. The papers focus on Dodd's personal work and contain little documentation of her involvement with Tanager Gallery. Found are biographical materials, including an interview conducted by Pat Mainardi in 1973; personal business records; professional correspondence; project and teaching files for Artist Housing Projects and various teaching positions; scattered writings and notes; printed materials including exhibition catalogs and announcements; and photographs.
Provenance
Lois Dodd donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in several increments between 1981-2007.
Related Material
Among the collections of the Archives of American Art are the Tanager Gallery records, 1952-1972 and an oral history interview with Lois Dodd by Barbara Shikler conducted in 1988.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Lois Dodd (1927- ) is an observational painter, educator, activist, and co-founder of the Tanager Gallery. She is active in New York City and Maine.
Lois Dodd was born in 1927 in Montclair, New Jersey. Beginning in 1945, Dodd commuted from Montclair to New York City to attend The Cooper Union, from which she graduated in 1948. She married fellow student and sculptor William King with whom she had one child, Eli. King and Dodd, among others, established the Tanager Gallery in 1952.
Dodd worked for various organizations in New York City promoting affordable housing for artists, especially the renewal of Cooper Square. She continues to exhibit her paintings at both individual and group exhibitions.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York City painter, educator, gallery owner, and activist Lois Dodd date from 1949 to 2001 and measure 2.0 linear feet. The papers focus on Dodd's personal work and contain little documentation of her involvement with Tanager Gallery. Found are biographical materials, including an interview conducted by Pat Mainardi in 1973; personal business records; professional correspondence; project and teaching files for Artist Housing Projects and various teaching positions; scattered writings and notes; printed materials including exhibition catalogs and announcements; and photographs.
Notable correspondents include Lucien Day, Rackstraw Downes, James McGarrell, James L. Lentz, and Sidney Simon.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1949-1989 (Box 1; 9 folders)
Series 2: Personal Business Records, 1950-1990 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Correspondence, 1952-1991 (Box 1; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Project and Teaching Files, 1969-1983 (Box 1-2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Writings and Notes, circa 1970-1990 (Box 2; 5 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1970-2001 (Box 2; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1952-circa 1990 (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Artists' studios--Photographs; Artists--Housing--New York (State)--New York; Gallery owners--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Women painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Interviews; Photographs
Names:
Day, Lucien B., 1916-; Downes, Rackstraw; Mainardi, Patricia, interviewer.; McGarrell, James, 1930-; Simon, Sidney, 1917-1997
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Information, 1949-1989, Series 1:; (Box 1; 9 folders)
  Found are records concerning awards, memberships, and certificates; biographical sketches and resumes; and personal materials including a driver's license from Maine, travel papers concerning Dodd's trip to Italy, and a transcript of a 1973 interview of Dodd by Pat Mainardi.
  - Awards, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Sketches, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificates, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Drivers License, Maine, before 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership Records, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    (includes ribbon)
  - Resumes, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Travel Papers, 1949-1960, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Interview Transcript, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Personal Business Records, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  Found are Lois Dodd's loan and exhibition agreements, contracts, donation records, gallery plans, lists, purchase orders, receipts, sales records, and shipping records. Also found is a file of correspondence and agreements for the publishing of Dodd's print Laundry.
  - Agreements, Exhibitions, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Agreements, Loans, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Concerning Laundry, 1984, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Contracts, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Donations, Works of Art, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Donations, Monetary, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gallery Plans, circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Price Lists, 1987-1990, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - List of Artists Exhibiting, 1968-circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Purchase Order, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Shipping Receipts, 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Receipts, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Delivery Confirmation Receipts, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Sales Records, 1974-1990 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Shipping Notes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.7 linear feet)
  Found are incoming and drafts of outgoing correspondence, the majority of which focuses on Dodd's painting career. Some personal correspondence may also be found. Notable correspondents include Lucien Day, Rackstraw Downes, James McGarrell, James Lentz, and Sidney Simon. Invitations to serve as art juror and to exhibit are found at the end of the series. Correspondence is also found in the project and teaching files.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence, 1988, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, circa 1950s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Invitations, Art Juror, 1979-1990 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Invitations, to Exhibit, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Postcards, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Project and Teaching Files, 1969-1983, Series 4:; (Box 1-2; 0.2 linear feet)
  Project files concern Dodd's work with the five Artist Housing Projects, including the Cooper Square Renewal and one file concerning a mural at Citibank. Files contain corresondence, publicity materials, clippings, and drafts of writings. Teaching files include materials from Dodd's positions at Brooklyn College, City University of New York, the Cleveland Institute of Art, Colby College, Louisiana State Univeristy, the Skowhegan School of Painting, and the Vermont Studio School, and may include correspondence and financial materials.
  - Artist Housing Projects (Box 1)
    - Cooper Square Renewal, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Cooper Square Renewal, Wyoming Building, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - "Museum," 1969 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Soho Lofts, 1969-1983 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Westbeth, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Other Projects (Box 1)
    - Citibank Mural, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Teaching Positions (Box 2)
    - Brooklyn College, 1973-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - City University of New York, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cleveland Institute of Art, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Colby College, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Louisiana State University, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Skowhegan School of Painting, 1979-1988, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Vermont Studio School, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1970-1990, Series 5:; (Box 2; 5 folders)
  Scattered writings include a statement of plans by Dodd and a draft of a speech by Joe Fiori.
  - Statement of Plans, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Notes, Concerning Italian Grant, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Speech Notes, Joe Fiori, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Writings, circa 1970s-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Notes, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Printed Material, circa 1970-2001, Series 6:; (Box 2; 0.6 linear feet)
  Printed materials include invitations, announcements, and catalogs for exhibitions of Dodd's work, including solo and group shows, as well as exhibitions of other artists. Also found are clippings, flyers, newsletters, and press releases. Of note are two publications featuring articles about and an interview with Dodd.
  - Invitations, 1977-1990, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1970-1994, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-21)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1981-2001, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
  - Auction Catalog, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Business Cards, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Blank Stationery, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, 1969-1988, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Flyers and Info Sheets, circa 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Magazine Articles About Dodd, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Programs, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Press Releases, 1968-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
  - Italian Materials, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    (Includes a blueprint of a ship and a pamphlet)
  - American Artist, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    (Includes article on Lois Dodd by Laurie Hurwitz)
  - Bench Press Series on Ar t, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    (Interviews with Bernadette Mayer and Lois Dodd)
- Photographs, 1952-circa 1990, Series 7:; (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
  There are personal snapshots and professional portraits of Lois Dodd and of Dodd with Bill and Eli King, Ann Arnold, Lee Bontecon, Angelo Ippolito, and others. Also found are photos of Dodd with her artwork and in her studio, and of works of art by Dodd and others.
  - Lois Dodd, Portraits, 1965-1975 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    (Includes potraits in her studio)
  - Lois Dodd, Portraits, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    (Includes potraits in her studio with works of art. Photos by Bob Brooks)
  - Lois Dodd and Bill King, circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Lois Dodd and Eli King, 1952-circa 1954, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
  - Lois Dodd, Lee Bontecon, Ann Arnold, by Mozette Tawil, circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Lois Dodd and Angelo Ippolito, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Lois Dodd and Others, 1957-1969 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Angelo Ippolito and Anita (no last name), 1952 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Interior of Summer Studio, Cushing, Maine, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Auction, Cushing, Maine, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Works of Art, by Lois Dodd, circa 1960-1979, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 50-52)
  - Works of Art, by Others, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 53)
Other Finding Aid
Bibliography